In today's video we will talk about Public
Sector Insurance Companies vs Private
Sector Insurance Companies.  Many times you get
confused as to which sector to
go with, the public sector which is
government owned insurance companies or the
private sector which is privately
insured insurance companies.
With whom should you take insurance?
Which is more trustworthy?
Who has more credibility?  Who
can be trusted when it comes to claims
?  We are going to talk about
which site you should visit.
So before starting the video I would
like to give a disclaimer.  I am
not promoting any sector
or any insurance company here.
I am just
telling you what are the advantages and
disadvantages of each.  Which one should be chosen by whom and at what time?
I am giving you a direction.  The
rest of the due diligence is your job.
[Music]
So let's go to the video.  Public sector
insurance companies as we talked about
are government owned insurance companies.  United India, Oriental
Insurance, New India and National
Insurance.  These are four companies which are public
sector.  Then there are 33 insurance
companies which are privately held.  Out
of which 28 are general insurance companies and
five are stand-alone health insurance
companies.  So 33 are your private sector
companies.  Such as HDFC Ago, ICICI
LBAT, Aitya Birl, Nib, C's Halth, ST
and so on.  So there are so many companies available.  There is indeed
confusion, which means it is
absolutely natural that there will be confusion.
So now we will talk about
what are the benefits of which sector and
from which perspective should which sector be seen.  Firstly,
what used to happen generally earlier, because earlier there were only public
sector insurance companies, so only
public sector insurance companies were chosen.
Then gradually private sector
companies started coming and people
started moving to the private sector.
So what was the advantage of the public sector
?  Premiums are comparatively lower
because these are government owned companies,
so the premiums are subsidized.  After that
your trust is more.  Like when people used to
take life insurance, it is still there.  In fact, the
major stakeholder in life insurance is
still LIC.  Private companies
are still less.  Slowly increasing.  Because
people have more trust in LIC.  It is
not that private companies are not credible.
But the trust that people have built is that it is an
old company, it is a government company, it does
not go anywhere, money does not sink.  So that
thought process is that mindset.  Similarly, there are
some people in health insurance who stick to the
old school of thought.  Those who
know, who have experience in government companies
or who have been
running them for years.  Meaning, you have been holding a health insurance policy for 40-50 years.  There
are such policy holders also.  Senior citizens
generally you will see they want to stick to the
same company.  They don't want to shift to
private insurance company.  That is his own
mindset.  So no one is good or bad.  There
is a nationwide presence.  You will find it
everywhere.  You will find their offices.
You will also find offices of these companies in tier two and tier three cities.  There is a nationwide
presence, lower premiums, and a trust
factor due to which people
buy or used to buy public sector companies.  Let us talk about it now
because many
things have changed over the years.  Earlier there was a basic health
insurance policy which very few people used to take.
Even now, if we talk about insurance penetration,
only 4% of the people are
insured in India.  So earlier it was even
less.  There
was no insurance awareness.  So taking insurance was
considered a big thing.  So if seen from that point of view,
earlier very few people were
insured and generally they used to take
insurance from public sector companies only.
These four companies had the major share.
Now gradually you are seeing that share is
shifting to private health
insurance companies.  What is its reason?
Many new things will be added.  Many of
our needs increased.  Public sector
companies generally have some sub limits.
Your room rent is capped.  Only 1% of sum
assured will be given.  Only 2% of sum assured will be
given.  What will be in it?  If
the policy is worth Rs 5 lakh, you will get a room worth Rs 5,000.  Ok
?  ICU will be available for Rs 10,000.  So you also
know that nowadays you cannot get a room for Rs 5,000 in any good hospital.
You can go to any decent hospital.  There
is no room below Rs 10 to 15,000.  And more so because the
entire bill of health insurance is
defined on the room basis.  So keeping that in
mind people started shifting to
private insurance companies.  Secondly, there are many
disease wise sublimits that only this much will be
given for this disease.  They will only
give this much for this disease which was
eliminated from the private insurance company.
He said we will provide comprehensive coverage.  They will
definitely charge higher premiums
but will provide you comprehensive coverage.
Some modern treatments and robotic
surgeries have come into existence which were not covered by government companies earlier.
Still covers it.
But to a certain percentage depends on the
policy to policy.  Many riders have also been
introduced now.  Earlier,
public sector companies did not have riders.  Whatever it
is, it is a product.  It was not a tailor-made product
that this product is.  You take this.
This is its premium.  Now they have
also come out with tailor made solutions that you have to
take this add on.  You choose.  It has
such a premium.  And so on considering the
market demand,
they also tried to change their product accordingly.
One disadvantage of public sector companies was
that they had external
TPS.  There is an insurance company and
they have a TPA.  There is a third party
administrator who settles the claims.
So as a policy holder you are
coordinating with the TPA as well as the
insurance company.  So the turnaround time was
longer.  For example, if you have to settle a claim,
you will also connect with the TPA.  If the
TPA says that
some returns are to come from the insurance company, then it would take more time
in the entire triangle.  Now what has happened is that the
private sector companies have
set up in-house TPAs.  Firstly, their cost
seems less because there is no external agency.
Secondly, claim settlement is faster.
You will find fewer digital options in the public sector.  If you
still want to file a claim set, then
you will have to submit a form to the
insurance company's office, which
is a little TDS process nowadays.
Private sector companies have come to the same place
where if we talk about their benefits, it
is completely digital.  You
can do absolutely everything online.  99% of claims are
filed online.  There is 1% where
physical documents have to be submitted.  Secondly,
all limits have been removed.  You were
given all the options.  Flexibility was given that this
flexibility is available.  You have to
get this cover by paying extra premium.
You have to avail some value
add on services by paying extra premium.  Which was earlier missing
in public sector policies.  So
now you can buy value orders by paying extra premium.  We have
brought innovative products
like if you need OPD coverage,
maternity coverage, what not, whatever
you need, you will
get it as an add-on in your policy.  The basic product in your policies is
very simple.  There are
17-1 add ons coming on top of that.  Private
companies that are launching.  The
same old policies are in place in the public sector.  There are no such
new products launched with innovation and lots of new features.
You have all the options available in private companies.  It is
digital friendly so
you can buy it in completely digital mode.
It can be operated only in digital mode.  There
is fast claim settlement.  Like I said,
you don't have a TPA.  There
is no third party administrator.  So there is fast claim
settlement.  There is no third party
involved in between.  There is coordination between you and the insurance
company.  And
Better Network Hospitals.  The
tie up with hospitals is better.
If we talk about disadvantages,
what are the disadvantages?  The cost is higher.  Definitely, if
you are getting something extra, some
value add-on, then its cost is
higher.  Many times there may be some hidden clauses
as there are many benefits.
You wouldn't go with such a broad policy wording.
If 50 pages of a 60-page
policy are wording, you won't be able to read all the pages.
So there may be some hidden clauses.
So that is why it is important for you to read the entire tholi.
Because earlier the products were quite simple.
You took it in a simple way.  Now there are equally many
complexes.   As
more benefits have been added, the
complexities have also increased.  So it
is important for you to read the policy wording when you are
buying a health insurance policy.
When will you find online agents of public sector companies?  Meaning, generally they were old agents
like LIC agents or if
you say there was an uncle in your family,
he used to do insurance for public sector companies.
Younger agents
deal less with the public sector
because of these disadvantages.  So
if you want to deal digitally, you will
find more agents of private sector companies as compared
to public sector companies.  So here
I am not saying that the public
sector is not good or the private sector is
not good.  This is just my opinion
which I am telling you what I have observed
over the years.  Rest of the final
policy will be taken only after due diligence.
I made a quick little comparison.  If we
talk about premium, there is
comparatively lower premium in the public sector.   There
is a slightly higher premium in the private sector.  Turnaround time is
longer in public sector companies.   It
costs less in private companies.  Network
hospitals are a little less.
You have larger options in public companies than you do in private companies.
More options are available.
You will get less digital services.
You will get everything digitally enabled in public companies and private sector companies.
You can do everything digitally.
Gradually public companies are also
getting there.  Meaning, for the things that earlier you had to
go to their office for everything.
A lot of things have moved online.
Customer support works in a similar manner for both.
Regarding the third party,
I mentioned that public sector companies
still operate on third party administration which
is TPA.
Where the claim settlement is being done by a third party.  There
is an external TPA.  Ware Ace
Private Companies is your internal TPA.
They have an in-house claim settlement team.  So
public sector companies are generally preferred for
senior citizens.  Those who have been
believing in him for years.  The
policy has been the same for 30-40 years.  They don't want to
change.  They prefer public sector companies
only for those who want the peace of mind that they
know they will get their claim.
Whatever happens, the claim does not go anywhere.  That
confidence remains intact and there is also a little budget
constraint, which leads to a slightly lower premium.  But
this is a myth.  Now in the coming time
you will see that premiums are increasing for everyone.
In fact, the prices of public companies as well as
private sector companies are increasing.  So
those who do not want to take any risk will go
to the public sector company.  And where
we talk about the
young generation in private sector companies, who are tech savvy, who
want digital facilities, who
want value adds, who want to cover not just their
illness but also their wellness.  There are
many such policies
where you also get gym membership.  If
you walk a few steps daily,
you get discounts.  You
get OPD cover.  Maternity cover
is available.  And what not, whatever you want, you
get international coverage.  You can get all the world wide coverage you
want in the policy.  So
those people prefer private companies.
And another thing in public companies is that
your assured sum does
not increase easily.  It takes a lot of time to increase the sum assured that you have received.  It
grows slowly, slowly.  If you want
1 crore, 2
crore, 3 crore in a private company, you will easily get it as per the
underwriting guidelines.  Now this is a matter of
public versus private.  There are some
universal rules that apply to both.
Whenever you are going to take health insurance
policies.  These are five things
that will help you a lot.  I have covered this many times
in many of my videos.
But I would like to rewrite it again.  The
first is the claim settlement ratio,
what is the claim settlement ratio of the
company you are going with and
what is their incurred claim ratio.  What other
things are covered?  What things are
not covered?  Third, there is no room rent limit.  It is
not that you will go there and
find out that there is a room rent limit there.
So you may have to pay a lot of money from your pocket.
Fourth, whenever you are taking any policy,
take it with full disclosure.
Fill your proposal form yourself.
Fill it properly and take the policy with full disclosure.
So that you do not face any problem in claims.
Fifth, check your add-ons to see
which ones you need.
Because a lot of you want to put
toppings on top of what you've been given is vanilla ice cream.  There
is chocolate, sprinkles
, cherries, you can add whatever toppings you like.
So there are many
interesting add ons which can
also save you money.  Of late annual health checkup is an
add on.  If you add that.  If you take
care of your health, it is possible that you may
not have to make any claims in the future.  So all these
things are small things but you can take care of them.  If
you need OPD coverage,
you can avail it.  Be sure to check out the
add-ons and which ones are essential for you.
So if a verdict has to be given in the end then there is
no verdict here.  It
is your choice, your priority, your
convenience, your cost factor.  Whatever you
feel is right for you, whatever
fits your needs,
buy that only.  But don't forget to do your due diligence.
And
never take any health insurance policy on non-disclosure basis.
This is what I just wanted to share with you.  If
you want to consult our team
then there are contact numbers and Google forms.
Please fill it.  Our team will reach
out to you.  And before we go, a quick
reminder, if you haven't subscribed to our channel yet, please do so.
So that you
get the right information at the right time.
See you in the next video.  Till then stay
safe, take care.  Baba bye.